I hate that colour.
But why do think they're so popular?
Cos they fit on a piece of bread.
That's right.
I mean, it's that...
It's that square shape, isn't it?
See if you can find a bug in there.
Bug free?
No.
Insect free?
Brilliant.
Well, I'm going to reveal the secrets behind supermarket food, by making the ingredients that go into a sandwich.
If you've ever baked your own bread, you probably prefer this to the supermarket bread.
But the problem with this stuff is that it goes rock hard in a day or so, while the supermarket bread...
Well, that stays soft for ages.
'So, what have they done to supermarket bread to make it stay softer than home-baked bread?
'To reveal what they're really doing to our food, I've come up with a surprising idea.
'I've set up my own food factory inside this barn.
'So, it's the battle of the breads.
'Homemade versus factory-made.
'Rock hard versus stay soft.
'I prefer making homemade bread, 'but it doesn't stay soft for ages like supermarket bread does.
'I'm going to try and discover why.'
Now, making bread is fairly easy, because you need very few ingredients.
For home baked bread you only need flour, water and yeast.
'When you add water to flour, it gets sticky and stretchy.
'It's this change which makes bread possible.
'Working the dough makes it stretchier.'
Look at that.
And that's formed by me pushing the dough backwards and forwards and being quite rough with it.
That's done.
Now what I'm going to do is pop it in this bowl here and let that rise.
'Experts decided they could reinvent bread.
'They could make it quicker and stay fresh longer.'
A research team in Chorleywood in Hertfordshire were trying to work on a new method of mass producing bread when they came up with a unique mixer machine.
Now, I'm going to try and have a go at my own version of this using this bin.
'I'm going to have to build a high power mixing machine with super strong mixing blades.
'These blades will help beat lots of extra air bubbles into the dough to make it lighter.'
To get the mixing power I need, I'm going to use this beast of a drill.
'My barn-built version of the Chorleywood machine 'will mix the dough faster and more vigorously than working the dough by hand.
'But supermarket bread needs more than high power mixing 'to make it stay soft.
'It has more ingredients than home baked bread.'
This is bread improver and it really makes supermarket bread supermarket bread.
In here are lots of different ingredients.
And they're on the back of the packet here.
So, we've got fats and emulsifiers.
And what they do, they make the air bubbles evenly spaced, small and airtight.
And that keeps the bread nice and springy.
And stops it going stale.
'The added ingredients make a big difference.
'I'm beginning to see why supermarket bread is so different to home baked bread.
'Hopefully my machine is going to thrash the mix really vigorously... 'if the mixing blades don't get stuck in the sticky dough.'
Right, I almost feel too scared to push the button now.
Here we go, nice and slow to start off with.
Now it's starting to change.
Its consistency's moving.
It's gone from quite an inanimate lump of sticky goo into something very, very elastic.
Wow.
Well, I reckon that has worked a treat.
It's really expanded and you can see where the mixing arms have thrashed it.
Agh!
Right, this is like lifting... ..the biggest marshmallow you've ever met in your life out of a dustbin.
Well, that's exactly what it is.
Look at that.
And it's so sticky and stretchy.
'Although it's sticky, it's light, 'so it must be full of those air bubbles.
'I can't just stick it in the oven though.
'Just like my handmade dough, it has to rest for an hour.
'But handmade dough takes longer, 'because it has to be worked for a second time.'
This home making of bread isn't an instant thing.
It does take a while.
'So, after resting for an hour, 'what has my supermarket bread dough turned out like?'
Wow, look at that!
It looks like a monster!
'There's only one thing left to do to this baby - bake it.'
Right.
20 minutes, half an hour.
That should do it.
'We'll come back to the battle of the breads 'to see how my supermarket bread turns out.'
'Now I'll find out what they're doing 'to the insides of my sandwich to make life so convenient.
'We're growing tomatoes almost all year round now.
'But how can UK growers sell them at a price that we can afford?
'The heating bills must be astronomical.'
Because you need extra heat to grow tomatoes out of season, it makes them more expensive.
And that's one reason why the vast majority of tomatoes we buy in the UK have been imported from overseas.
John Jones at Guy & Wright in Hertfordshire supplies two of the biggest supermarkets.
To get the best performance from the fruit and the plant, we need to give the plant everything that it needs.
The right heat, the right humidity control.
The right feed in the slab.
So, your job, your main job, is to cater for every single need of this tomato plant?
That's it.
We nurture it.
'Turning up the heating to simulate summer on this scale costs a fortune.
'As the price of fuel rockets, John's tomatoes might simply become too expensive.
'But he's come up with an ingenious idea.
'He's recycling waste fruit and veg from large wholesale markets and overripe imported foods.'
What's wrong with these?
Well, those in particular are ones that we've just de-boxed this week.
They actually came from the docks.
And they were too ripe.
They were too ripe?
You see, I don't think they're ready for eating yet.
'I'm staggered by how much of this waste there is.
Have we gone completely bananas?'
Look at all this.
It's hard to believe that this is actual waste, you know?
These have come from overseas, the Caribbean.
And because they're probably not just perfect, they're thrown out.
I mean, some of them aren't even ripe yet.
Look at these ones.
Still green.
And you open them up.
Look at this.
Open that up... and there's nothing wrong with it whatsoever.
It seems criminal.
There's something seriously wrong when we're wasting this amount of food.
And it's not just bananas.
But at least we can put them to some use.
'John has come up with a way to use this wasted fruit and veg to heat his glasshouses, 'saving a fortune in fuel.'
'The bananas are tipped into this giant hopper 'along with tons of other fruit and veg that would otherwise go into landfill, 'and then mashed into a pulp.'
So this is where you make a great big banana smoothie, is it?
'The liquid is held in here...'
You wouldn't eat a spoonful of that, would you?
'..And then pumped into concrete tanks underground.
'Inside the tanks, trillions of bacteria feed on the waste, 'giving off lots of highly flammable methane gas.'
Wow, look at that.
Looks like tar from down there, doesn't it?
The methane gas is burnt to produce electricity, which is then used to heat all the glasshouses.
By burning the methane, John is producing a lot of carbon dioxide, and here's one of John's really clever ideas.
Tomatoes ripen much more quickly when there's extra carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.
So he pumps the waste gas into the glasshouses.
The plants absorb the carbon dioxide and produce a lot more tomatoes.
So, providing this micro climate, how does it affect your productivity?
We can achieve in a block like this... which is an acre... almost 300 tons out of here.
And what would that have been like say 40 years ago?
60, 70.
Really?
60 or 70.
That increase?
So, I'm really shocked to see the amount of rejected fruit and veg which turns up here every week.
But I suppose, thanks to John's ingenuity, it's not wasted.
It's the battle of the breads.
Why does supermarket bread stay soft, while home baked bread goes stale?
The secret is the super speedy mixing, which traps more air in the dough and the added ingredients which helps stop the bread drying out.
My supermarket bread is ready to come out of the oven, but the hand-mixed dough still has to rest for another half an hour.
Right, I'm quite excited about this.
Let's have a look.
Oh, my word!
I think I've created a monster.
Look at this!
Do you know what?
I don't know what to say.
I don't know whether to be proud or ashamed.
Look at it.
Right.
It seems nice and... nice and cooked.
There, look at that.
Well, the bottom half looks all right.
The top half looks like an abomination.
'The dough was so deceptively light and springy, 'I think I put too much in the tin.'
But one thing for sure is that this process is incredibly quick.
I mean, these are my two loaves here.
They're just still proving really.
This little... ha!
This little monster has been mixed, it's risen and it's been baked in a fraction of the time.
'If it looks like this outside, what on earth does it look like inside?
Oh, yeah, actually no.
That's not too bad at all.
Look at that.
That's a really good network of bubbles.
Well, I reckon doesn't matter if it's a bit ugly, that is a success.
Do you know what?
That is a really good loaf.
Luckily I mixed so much dough, I actually filled two tins.
But I put a lot less in this one.
Smaller sister, much better looking.
There we are.
Look at that.
That's more like it.
Perfect.
Not too sure about the ugly sister though.
Soft and sliced, just like the supermarket.
There you go, my supermarket loaf.
'But mine won't really be as good as the supermarket bread unless it stays soft for over a week.
'So here comes the real test.'
Nine days ago, I made supermarket bread.
Now, let's see how it's got on.
Now, this is real supermarket bread which was bought on the same day.
Let's have a look.
Softish.
Starting to go off, that.
This is my version of supermarket bread.
Let's have a look.
Let's just take one at random.
Smells fresh, still soft.
But look at this.
This is the bread made to a traditional farmhouse recipe.
Hard as a rock.
'So it's the battle of the breads.
'Pick your winner - home baked bread or supermarket bread?'
Right, that's the bread sorted.
But what are they doing to the insides of our sandwiches?
Now I've heard that salad leaves are treated with chemicals and sprayed with tons of pesticides to make sure we never get a bug in our bagged salad.
Well, I wanted to find out if this was really true.
Every summer, this salad producer wages daily war against enemy bugs.
Defending their 400-mile-long front demands a military campaign.
Week in week out, Vitacress supply a million and a half packs of tender leaves to supermarkets.
They deploy intelligence gathering, covert operations and some heavy armaments to stop the invading bugs from infiltrating their bags.
Now, if you're a pest that likes eating salad, then this is gourmet heaven.
But how do you get the pests off when it comes to harvest time?
The battle commences as soon as the lettuce seed is sown.
These simple flags signal the start of hostilities.
These sticky yellow squares are a low-tech, high-tack solution to trapping insect problems.
These camouflaged bat boxes house a squadron of airborne allies.
During their nightly sorties every enlisted bat can pick off up to 3,000 insects.
Sam is commander of field operations.
His job is to stop enemy bugs and insects from destroying the crop, but he must spray as little pesticide as possible.
After inspection, he orders me to wear protective headgear.
Here, have a hat.
A present?
It's to stop contamination getting into our crops.
Sam enlists undercover reinforcements.
As long as he sows wild flower seeds, they will willingly set up camp and eat other pests for their rations.
This is a vetch plant.
These are attracting beneficial insects such as ladybirds and your hover flies, which eat aphids and keep them out of our crops.
So you rely on nature to... to help you out basically?
Where possible we'll use nature and natural ways of controlling pests.
They do use pesticides here, but this arsenal of natural weapons reduces the need for spraying.
When the salad crop is ready for bagging, the really heavy artillery comes out.
Heavy metal weaponry announces the arrival of the harvester.
The clanking chains shake the leaves and frighten off the enemy.
Now, as the machine moves along the rows, it pushes all the leaves of the lettuce backwards and forwards.
And that drives all those insect pests away.
But Sam's work isn't done yet.
He's determined to make sure none of the bugs end up in a bag.
But when you're harvesting 50,000 kilos a day, some of the blighters are bound to slip through.
The next stage, as you see here, is the second bouncing belt.
This bouncing belt has holes that are small enough to let the leaf carry on going up, but large enough to let insects fall through.
This is an impressive defensive display.
But I can't believe a really determined bug hanging onto its lunch won't get through.
But Sam reassures me there's even more in store.
The secret to keeping freshly cut leaves from wilting is to get them really cold and fast.
Production manager Steve says target temperature is one degree C within the hour, but even the extreme cold doesn't eliminate the bugs.
The colder we make the leaves, the colder the insects are that have got caught up in the harvest.
So they effectively go to sleep.
They're lying there passively on or amongst the leaves.
Not moving, they're harder to spot.
So, I mean, what's the largest creature that's actually come through here?
Well, every so often we'll get a frog caught up in the harvest.
Remarkably they come through the vacuum process unharmed, hopping at the other end.
Well, the last thing you want is to open a bag of salad and a frog leaps out.
Exactly.
The final push is at the packing plant.
Even here a sleepy slug or a brave bug might still hope to wake up inside a bag.
The leaves are immediately subjected to high-tech interrogation.
So the leaves have been unloaded and they're cascading over this conveyer belt into this machine.
What does this bit of kit do?
Basically it's using state of the art cameras and software equipment, taking a photo 4,000 times a second of the leaves.
4,000 times a second it takes a snap?
Yeah.
They're all then fed into the computer system, looking for defects, looking for insects or any problems with the leaf.
If it spots what it sees is a insect or a defect, it sends a blast of air to the right place on the conveyer belt to eject that defect or leaf.
Bagged salad got a bad reputation when it was revealed that some producers wash it in mild bleach.
But here the leaves are pampered in a bath of pure spring water.
We have a sub merger wheel, which is a mesh wheel that pushes the leaves under the water, and gives a chances for any buoyant insects to come up and be separated.
So, the washing process is the final process.
Yeah.
That's the last in a whole series of what we call hurdles really.
So it's very unlikely that anything will have got by all the lines of defences we erect.
With so many hurdles to jump, and so many packs, I calculate you'd have to buy a bag a week for 1,442 years before you'd be likely to find a bug in your bag.
The last stage of production is to get the salad leaves in the bags.
So, this is the final process.
They're about to go off to the supermarket?
Yeah, basically.
The leaves have been spun to get rid of the surplus water.
They're pre-weighed up above us.
They're dropping down that tube.
And as they fall they're being dropped into preformed bags.
Final product going by on the conveyer.
So each bag should be totally bug free?
Yup.
That's what we aim to achieve.
Well, fingers crossed, eh?
'So, if a bug does make it all the way into your bag, don't be cross.
'Congratulate him!'
No bugs.
Walk down the cheese aisle of any supermarket and you'll find everything from blocks of cheese like this to this stuff.
But what is the difference between normal cheese and processed cheese?
Two different types of cheese here.
What are the differences between the two?
It's maybe the flavour.
Right.
What about this one?
See, if I told you that was only 60% cheese...
Yeah?
..What do you think the rest of the 40% is made up of?
I don't know.
Who knows?
Yes.
Two bits of cheese here, OK?
Tell me what the differences are between them and...
Processed.
Not processed.
So, if I told you that that is only 60% cheese, what else do you reckon's inside it?
Water.
Water, yeah, yeah.
I haven't got a clue.
Salt.
Salt, yeah.
Don't really know.
To discover the difference between normal cheese and processed cheese, I'm going to make both here in the barn.
And I'll start with normal cheese.
Right, what I've got here is a glass of warm milk, but watch what happens when I put some lemon juice in it.
Now, give that a little stir.
Pass that through a sieve.
Now, the lemon juice has split this milk into two separate parts.
All that in there, that's the whey, and what's left behind in my sieve are all the curds.
That's what forms cheese.
And that's normal cheese.
The acid in the lemon juice causes the solids in the milk to separate from the liquid.
In the factory they make cheese in a big vat.
So, I've knocked up my own version using this heated tank.
Right, stirrer goes in.
Now, this milk won't turn to cheese on its own.
I need some help.
In fact, 100 billion helpers.
They're all in here.
Bacteria.
In the factory, they don't use lemon.
They use the bacteria I've added to this milk to produce acid.
The acid helps separate the curds from the whey.
There we go.
Right.
Last in, some rennet, which is a coagulant to help the curds solidify.
That's all in.
So far, the same as all cheese is made, and after a few minutes, a remarkable change takes place.
Now, when you first look at the milk it doesn't look any different, but that rennet has done it's job.
And let's just try something.
There we go.
Look at that.
And what has happened, it's set.
Almost like a blancmange.
Now I'm going to slice the cheese, so the liquid runs out.
You can really start to see you've got the big blocks, which are the curds, and that's separated from this liquid, the whey.
Now, I've got to get rid of as much of that whey as possible.
It's starting to shoot out in all different directions.
Now, it's starting to look like cheese.
Look at that.
I'll just squeeze out the last of the liquid.
Push that down.
And that's the recipe for normal cheese.
Now, if I was making regular cheese, I'd leave that for a month to mature, but I'm turning it into processed cheese.
So, what's the different between normal cheese and processed cheese?
Well, they look a bit different, and they behave a bit differently when you heat them.
Look, the fat doesn't seep out of the processed cheese, which is why it works well in hamburgers.
So, what do they do to normal cheese to turn it into processed cheese?
Processed cheese is only about 60% cheese.
Now, I'm going to turn my normal cheese into processed cheese by adding the other 40% of stuff the factory puts in.
Mostly it's water and some milk powder to bulk it up and make it softer.
This is what turns normal cheese into processed cheese.
'Fat and water don't mix.
'So I'm going to add these special melting salts.'
Blender on.
'The melting salts will help 'lock all the extra water into my normal cheese.'
But now it's time for my cheese.
As I heat them all up, I hope I'll end up with a smooth paste, with all the ingredients fully mixed together.
What have I done to my perfectly good cheese?
I've turned it into scrambled egg.
Surprisingly my normal cheese and the added water are binding together nicely.
The melting salts seem to be working.
Full power.
Right.
Something's changed here.
Stirring, stirring, stirring, and then this cheese is suddenly turned to quite a thick doughy consistency.
Look at that.
Really stringy.
Right.
I've got to act quickly now to pour this out before it goes rock hard.
It's actually quite hard to get out the bowl.
And this, believe it or not, is how they make processed cheese into slices.
Well, it's no masterpiece, but I reckon that's as close as I'm going to get.
'OK, it's a bit wrinkly, but not a bad colour.'
Look at that.
Now that would repair a tractor tire when it's got a puncture.
Look at this stuff!
Look how thick it is.
'Some of it's as thick as tractor tires, 'but this end isn't so bad.'
Let's see what it tastes like.
It feels like processed cheese.
It doesn't taste of a lot, but I'm really proud of how thin it is.
Look at that!
There we go.
My processed cheese slices.
Later we made up another batch to the same recipe.
To see if it would pass the taste test down on my farm.
I know you haven't quite eaten it yet.
But did you like the cheese?
It was creamy.
It's nice.
It's better than the normal processed cheese.
Bit rubbery for me, really.
Rubbery?
Rubbery.
What do you think of my cheese?
Yes.
You thought it was good?
Good.
What would you give me out of 10 for that cheese?
I'd say about 7.
Nine, ten.
Nine, ten!
Full marks?
Yeah.
Show me your hands.
All gone?
All gone, look.
That's just some of the clever science supermarkets use so that we can buy bread once a week, have cheese slices the perfect size and enjoy tomatoes out of season.
And eat salad without worrying about unwanted caterpillars.
I don't think I can look at the humble sandwich in the same way again.